<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>The Real Changes</title>
  <subtitle>A blog about life &amp; tech</subtitle>
  <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/" />
  <updated>2026-01-29T12:05:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Konstantin Ovchinnikov</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The TCO Thing</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-tco.html" />
    <updated>2026-01-29T12:05:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-tco.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first I had an idea to write a balancing article to my thoughts on opensource and custom solutions, to be a devil&#39;s advocate and to criticize myself. People choosing Windows, WordPress and ready-to-install systems can&#39;t be all wrong and they are not dumb for sure. And I thought I could prove their viewpoint with the TCO analysis, but then I had an intuitive feeling that I&#39;m missing something. If this TCO analysis is correct, why is it often disproved lately? And then it struck me: we are already in some &amp;quot;catastrophic&amp;quot; scenarios, but I&#39;m cheerful, so I&#39;ll call them post-apocalyptic scenarios (PAS). We are not living in post-apocalypse yet, although some people are building bunkers and there&#39;s a whole culture and community of &amp;quot;preppers&amp;quot;. But some changes are so drastic that they turn over the financial models, one of them being TCO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tco-model&quot;&gt;TCO model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical TCO model has two components, and that&#39;s a lot already: the cost of buying and the maintenance cost. I don&#39;t feel that&#39;s enough, so I&#39;d add two more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making a decision cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buying/development/implementation cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintenance/enhancement cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PAS maintenance/enhancement cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go really quick through it. First, you make a decision what to buy to fix your problem, and that involves costs: you need to become a minimal subject matter expert or to find one, you need to view some demos, find people you trust and ask them questions about how they feel using the product, find the reviews, create a &amp;quot;+/-&amp;quot; table, make your conclusions, get stuck in decision paralysis, find a way out, get stuck again and so on. &lt;strong&gt;Marketing&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;word of mouth&lt;/strong&gt; do a great job supplying you with information, so it seems like you know the right choice. They both fail with opensource solutions, for instance: opensource products often do not have paid marketing at all (be grateful for a neat GitHub page), most people you know may not know about it or even have a non-professional negative attitude (that&#39;s what marketing specialists of the other products are paid for) toward these products, yet the opensource product can beat a closed-source one in product-market fit, being (mostly) free for acquisition cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buying phase is exploited by marketing as well: you visit a nice office, drink free coffee, have a talk with nice people, then you conveniently pay a large amount of money (assuming you can&#39;t be screwed if you pay this large amount), you get your license key or even a box. So, you have a box on the shelf, nothing works. Well, you have to pay for some consulting, but they will not do the work for you; in the case of an ERP system they will not figure out what to do with your 50 incompatible item directories. But they got the money, they are happy, and you are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been implementing the best ERP systems available on the market since 2003, and I strongly believe in custom solutions, because they have three traits &amp;quot;pre-packaged&amp;quot; or even &amp;quot;customizable&amp;quot; solutions don&#39;t have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You start to understand your requirements during development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can create something unique, supporting your unique competitive advantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tech stack of most &amp;quot;pre-packaged&amp;quot; solutions is pretty old, and you are free to leverage the advancements in technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B2B moves at a slower pace and there are reasons to have a &amp;quot;pre-packaged&amp;quot; solution as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A stable tech stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standardized supporting processes to deal with your contractors easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out your requirements from the software description&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the killing argument for a &amp;quot;pre-packaged&amp;quot; solution is the maintenance cost, because talented developers are not willing to support their software, they are willing to write new software. So eventually you&#39;ll lose even the ability to fix bugs in your custom solution. But that&#39;s not the case if IT is the core part of your business, and you put consistent effort and budget into its enhancement. Many retailers do it, some logistics companies do it, and they can be quite successful. Just don&#39;t slow down, because freezing is death for your product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Effort&amp;quot; is a key word here. So, if you have a lot to do and you are not willing to put a lot of effort into software development, is the &amp;quot;pre-packaged&amp;quot; option still good? Well, it is, if we do not consider PAS. PAS changes a lot, not only TCO. But how to predict PAS?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-predict-pas&quot;&gt;How to predict PAS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2022 I had a task from an IT company as a part of the hiring process: make a presentation for a potential new product. And I wrote that a war in Ukraine is possible and we should probably have a backup plan for the product in this scenario. How did I do that? Well, it&#39;s simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PEST analysis (politics, economics, society, tech) – just read the news, bro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SWOT analysis: how can external factors from PEST impact the product or the company? SWOT analysis normally includes internal factors as well, but for PAS they are mostly irrelevant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russian army was near the border of Unkraine, so there was information in the news that the probability of war is above zero. Why? Well, the troops have guns, and they shoot the guns, that&#39;s what they do if they have an order. Why place the troops and don&#39;t order them to shoot? It&#39;s called politics, but sometimes the politics ends and the war begins. I personally didn&#39;t believe that it would turn out this way, no one I knew believed and lots of strategically-thinking people didn&#39;t consider it an option, but it was there all the time and the probability turned into a matter of fact. And it was that easy to notice and predict; it was in the news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&#39;s usually some information about the probability of a PAS; the information is widely available, as it&#39;s a major event. What kind of event? Let&#39;s look at PEST again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War for politics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crisis for economics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Civil war as a consequence of radicalization for society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems hack/breakdown for tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We could add flood, earthquake, fire or meteorite for natural disasters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you are not still panicking or ordered the bunker already, what are these events about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-pas-brings&quot;&gt;What PAS brings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a book Trust by Francis Fukuyama. It&#39;s a shame I didn&#39;t read it, but I strongly recommend it. Here&#39;s my take on trust:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trust is a fundamental basis of the modern world (meaning all the letters from PEST)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fundamental flaw and the reason for poverty in the Global South is a lack of trust, and I observed it personally in Russia for 39 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In case of PAS the most damage it does is it breaks trust: in the government, economics, society or tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just remember the latest bug causing software breakdown in the airports. We have to pay with our time and money buying alternatives, moving slower or reserving funds for possible losses caused by such an event. Anyway, let&#39;s return to TCO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-pas-changes-tco&quot;&gt;How PAS changes TCO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mild economic crisis can cause many companies to cease to exist. Yes, they promised to support your software (or, worse, you used their online platform), but in the case of closed source you have nothing to do. A mild political crisis can turn tech giants against you, and that&#39;s why Europe is so &amp;quot;excited&amp;quot; about replacing software and SaaS services from the US with alternatives. It turns out, it doesn&#39;t take WWIII to be screwed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The older logic was reasonable: in the case of WWIII we won&#39;t need this software anyway. Well, gents who said that, what do you say now? The US sanctions against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.euronews.com/my-europe/2025/06/06/eu-deplores-us-sanctions-against-icc-judges-including-slovenian&quot;&gt;ICC judges&lt;/a&gt; don&#39;t have a symmetric response, because EU and US were partners and &lt;strong&gt;trusted&lt;/strong&gt; each other. Debanking, ban from apps and services. What&#39;s interesting is that it&#39;s a test, the same way lots of military technologies are sadly tested in Ukraine. Does it work? How do they react? That&#39;s valuable information. If you have this information, you are ahead of your opponents as you can leverage it. Opponents earlier considered partners, sad to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue with opensource is that technically it can be created by developers from the US, but you can still be independent. That&#39;s the trick, until anyone proves the opposite. You can put any sanctions you want on a country, but you can&#39;t prohibit it from using opensource solutions, and this case with the most heavily-sanctioned countries proves the point. The flawed logic is when one says &amp;quot;well, we&#39;ll always be on the other side, issuing sanctions&amp;quot;. I have news: &amp;quot;always&amp;quot; doesn&#39;t exist in PAS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software is a bunch of code, you need this code – it&#39;s an important point, we need to stop here for a moment – but you also need &lt;strong&gt;the competence&lt;/strong&gt; to modify this code, then you have all the degrees of freedom with your software solutions. I&#39;ve seen some software, notably JavaScript frameworks, which are opensource, the documentation exists, but to make money on it, the docs are brief and you are encouraged to obtain info via paid courses. That&#39;s not good enough! You need a leading technology for every area with a healthy independent community creating all the documents needed to reproduce all the results you want with the software. Yes, Linus Torvalds kicked all the Russia-based devs from the kernel team. Yes, independent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question: what do you need to create competence? There&#39;s a book by Quincy Larson &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/learn-to-code-book/&quot;&gt;How to Learn to Code and Get a Developer Job&lt;/a&gt; and he skyrocketed his career as a developer visiting hackathons and meetups. In the most introvert-filled industry, communication, communities and offline meetings are key. And I search through Eventbrite, Meetup.com in Germany and I cry, because &lt;strong&gt;there&#39;s nothing and it sucks&lt;/strong&gt;. There are some meetups in Berlin, Cologne and Munich probably, and I&#39;m in a rural area, and it can be the same in rural areas in the US. In any case, it&#39;s easier for me to find an English-speaking Discord group for Go development than to find anything online or offline in Germany. Is that the reason the US is so ahead of Europe regarding tech?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s another level of trust: people as sentient species build trust when they meet each other personally. My job is 99% communication and trust is essential for me. And the thing I hate the most is 30-minute online interviews – it&#39;s impossible to build any trust with this lack of presence and this lack of time. In Europe people often consider environmental impact more important than personal contact. The contact can be a reason for pollution, but abandoning it doesn&#39;t solve the problem. And it&#39;s sad to live in this &amp;quot;videoconference&amp;quot; world, the lack of trust and the lack of means to build it being the reason for this sadness. That&#39;s all I have to say.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>When You Let It Slip</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-slip.html" />
    <updated>2026-01-21T14:10:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-slip.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have something to say regarding the recent discussion on &amp;quot;digital European sovereignty&amp;quot; and the dependence of the EU on software from the US. More than that, I have several examples where, in a few major (and one minor) cases, people escaped this dependence. I have to make a few disclaimers though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m not into conspiracy theories, and I assume that the main motive for what&#39;s happening is money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&#39;t believe in external abstract evil, but I know for sure that evil exists inside me, and laziness is one of its implications (right now I&#39;m too lazy to exit the terminal and Neovim, for instance).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story itself is very old and has been described multiple times, but in Europe it still works: our client sends us a docx document, we need the money, so we have to have MS Office and MS Windows installed, whatever they are called now. But that&#39;s the decision point. I have a small outlook on this situation in European companies, and I feel like the management of these companies doesn&#39;t see a pivoting point here &lt;strong&gt;at all&lt;/strong&gt;, they just comply. And so it happens. There are a few efforts to migrate to Linux (mainly in the government), but just imagine the amount of license fees European companies, NGOs, and governmental structures pay for Microsoft and/or Apple. It&#39;s huge, and I don&#39;t see the point of not using Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-linux-ms-windows-and-ms-office-case&quot;&gt;The Linux/MS Windows and MS Office case&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, not being religious and evading conspiracies, I prefer Linux for being a better product as a desktop operating system. And DHH does too, having been an Apple evangelist earlier. And even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Bazzite/&quot;&gt;gamers migrate&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bazzite.gg/&quot;&gt;Bazzite&lt;/a&gt; being pissed off by Microsoft policy. For me, it&#39;s evident that the open source model just works better for an operating system, and for the desktop, you mostly need web apps nowadays, so it&#39;s more convenient and safer to run Linux for that. I still won&#39;t buy a Chromebook though, because not all the apps are online for my purposes, but for the B2B world, it&#39;s easier than ever to migrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The document format for exchange is still tricky, but especially for editing contracts, you could use apps to edit contracts collaboratively, and I&#39;ve seen quite a few people who know how to use the &amp;quot;compare versions&amp;quot; MS Word feature for that. PDF has also proved to be a good solution for document exchange, providing &amp;quot;the same look everywhere&amp;quot; experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument &amp;quot;everyone knows MS products&amp;quot; seems flawed to me. I&#39;m 43 years old, and I&#39;ve seen a few people who know how to use Word (at least structural markup and contents auto-generation), Excel (formulas), and PowerPoint (a few guys and gals from consulting, one of them being a designer from McKinsey). &amp;quot;Everybody writes it in their CV&amp;quot; is closer to reality to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used Linux when the Internet was delivered via dial-up modems and chatbots didn&#39;t exist. Now you can not only ask, you can generate a config file for anything effortlessly, so as &#39;modern AI&#39; (at least what we have now) lowered the bar to enter development, it has surprisingly unnoticed lowered the bar for a desktop Linux user. Linux software got more mature, hardware support got better (even in Debian, he he he). And as development became more accessible, it turned out that Linux on the desktop just works better for that. Meanwhile, MS Windows is turning into AI slop both from the inside (the code) and from the outside (UI/UX). I also play Minecraft on Linux and use cloud gaming, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tex-case&quot;&gt;The TeX case&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was there a case where Microsoft didn&#39;t get in with its standards? Well, the scientific society is a great example of that. They somehow managed to organize themselves on an international level, and only sources in TeX format are accepted. Someone has to write a fiction (probably a thriller) about that and name the real heroes who did that. As a scientist, you are free to write in MS Word and pay someone to typeset your text in TeX format, but you can&#39;t submit it in MS Word. Did Microsoft try to penetrate this market? I don&#39;t know, but I could assume it for the &amp;quot;follow the money&amp;quot; reason, and this market is huge as well, but someone &lt;strong&gt;didn&#39;t let it slip&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-usb-c-case&quot;&gt;The USB-C case&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU presents USB-C charging unification as a major win. It&#39;s a win, from a consumer perspective and from an environmental perspective (which rarely match). The same could be done for document formats, and the document unification/open document format initiative exists, but &lt;strong&gt;it slips&lt;/strong&gt;, not being enforced enough, in my humble opinion. Again, returning to USB-C: tough enforcing wasn&#39;t a problem there, rather one of the key success components, so fear it not. Microsoft wasn&#39;t able to repeat this &amp;quot;standards trick&amp;quot; with Internet Explorer, JavaScript, and HTML extensions, and IE as a product hopefully died, but Microsoft Office formats are still alive and well. I don&#39;t say they should die, I just say there&#39;s no way closed formats controlled by one company could be beneficial for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-humble-case&quot;&gt;My humble case&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Linux/MS Office/TeX rebellion story is nice, as it takes almost nothing to write an article about it in a blog nobody reads anyway. But that&#39;s not the case, I wrote all my diplomas in TeX and I had severe resistance in one particular institution. &amp;quot;Could you just pay someone to type it in Word?&amp;quot; asked the director of this institution. &amp;quot;You are not allowed to impose a closed format from a particular company&amp;quot; – that&#39;s exactly what I said (I&#39;ll not elaborate on my feelings in this moment, but as you can see I wasn&#39;t friendly at all). Did they have the power to make me? We don&#39;t know that, events happened in Russia where it&#39;s hard to say if anyone was concerned about using TeX for a diploma thesis. Did I pay for that? Yes, sure, but I was always a pain in the butt for them, so they made me collect all the signatures twice, rewrite half of my thesis in a week or so, and defend my thesis twice. My point is that &lt;strong&gt;you don&#39;t let it slip&lt;/strong&gt; by creating non-zero costs to make you use MS Word. They were in full control, but by doing this I somehow made it work my way. Could I have behaved myself &amp;quot;wisely&amp;quot; and complied? Sure, and I&#39;d have nothing to write about. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I don&#39;t believe in external evil, I have to acknowledge US corporations for contributing to society and open source with the products I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adobe for CSS and PDF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft for VS Code and TypeScript, Playwright and contributions to the Linux kernel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple for WebKit, LLVM, and CUPS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a whole other story how this &amp;quot;let it slip&amp;quot; thing happens – I mean the decision-making process it takes. I strongly believe we &lt;strong&gt;let ourselves slide first&lt;/strong&gt;, and then external &lt;strong&gt;compliance&lt;/strong&gt; (I don&#39;t use &amp;quot;shit&amp;quot; here for some reason) happens. Being not sincere to yourself is a way to go if you want circumstances to slide. But when these circumstances hit you back, don&#39;t complain – you deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d like to add a dramatic quote by myself to this nonsense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are living in a time of ignorance and false assumptions. And it is our tolerance that allows them to rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&#39;d like to thank George Orwell and Yevgeny Zamyatin for their books.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How I&#39;m Screening Out Vacancies</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-screening.html" />
    <updated>2026-01-19T17:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-screening.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to share my experience with applying for vacancies, because time and resources are obviously limited, and some descriptions cry out, &amp;quot;Do not apply here.&amp;quot; So here are the red flags I use for project management, but you&#39;ll get the idea and will be able to apply them to other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nothing in particular&lt;/strong&gt; means it&#39;s project management in IT, but there&#39;s no evidence of any other details. Managing IT services? Building infrastructure? Implementing solutions for business logic? Developing new digital products? After 22 years, I&#39;m sure all these areas require specific expertise, so the job description should be specific as well. You just can&#39;t write &amp;quot;IT Project Manager&amp;quot; and post it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mix of skills&lt;/strong&gt; is a great filter for greedy people. They want a project manager combined with a system admin and support. That&#39;s not &amp;quot;all-rounder&amp;quot; – you&#39;re just being greedy and unprofessional, so you&#39;ll get what you deserve: incompetence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not naming the system you implement&lt;/strong&gt;. These are not names of ERP systems: SAP, SAP ERP, M365. Why? Well, SAP is the name of the company, for instance. Again, the problem is that you need relevant experience to implement any ERP system, and the experience required is very different for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outdated tech stack&lt;/strong&gt;. This could be the most arguable one, but in my personal opinion, if you&#39;re sticking in 2026 with PHP, C#, RPA, or no-code, you just create more problems than you&#39;re trying to solve, so these projects are cursed from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strange name for the role&lt;/strong&gt;, like project coordinator or project controller instead of project manager, indicates a major misunderstanding, a probable lack of authority accompanied by full responsibility, as well as a possible intent to pay significantly less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developing an in-house ERP system&lt;/strong&gt; is like reinventing the bicycle, and from an economic viewpoint, it&#39;s not viable unless a company is a vast retail network. For a midsize construction company – definitely a no-go, and a waste of resources for a false objective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI buzz&lt;/strong&gt; – because that&#39;s not how it works. You don&#39;t replace people with AI, and you don&#39;t jump over &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2024-04-maturity.html&quot;&gt;maturity levels&lt;/a&gt;. You also can&#39;t compensate for incompetence with AI, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The End of the Midlife Crisis</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-crisis.html" />
    <updated>2026-01-04T14:50:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-crisis.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s very easy to define midlife: before it everything goes up, and after it – down. It has two dimensions, though: one being a decline of cognitive and physical abilities, but another is the expectations – you will probably not meet better people, watch better movies, read better books. There&#39;s only one Gravity Falls and The Three-Body Problem, guys. :) Chasing brighter impressions is dangerous, as it leads to drugs or high-adrenaline adventures, both being, in fact, running from yourself. So, passing the midlife crisis is about stopping running and accepting reality. Mistakes are hard to accept, but the good news is that now you (hopefully) have made enough of them to benefit from this experience and &lt;strong&gt;try&lt;/strong&gt; to do everything right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is this reality about, what&#39;s frightening us? This stuff is not necessarily negative, by the way. There&#39;s the deepest pool in the world, Deep Dive Dubai, and it has some inscriptions on the bottom for those who dive there. Metaphorically speaking, there are some bullet points at the bottom of the midlife crisis, and the end of the crisis doesn&#39;t happen without reading and accepting them. Thank God I had time to reflect on them, and thanks to my psychologist I had support and a baseline. So, here we go, without further comments and conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Family and parental roles are the most important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adulthood is about owning your mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most mistakes and their consequences can&#39;t be &amp;quot;fixed&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes there will be no external punishment for your mistakes, and you&#39;ll regret it the most&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody needs anyone; choosing a person as a friend or as a partner can only be a conscious choice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being with a person who didn&#39;t choose you is a mistake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving up your boundaries or breaking another person&#39;s boundaries is a mistake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having your own opinion and respecting yourself is important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing will change in your favour accidentally; if you want something to change, do it yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making a difference requires pushing through&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a job is important, as being paid is a simple sign that you do something valuable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You know everything life is offering you, and the most valuable things are pretty basic and don&#39;t cost much money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s easy to choose hobbies: those which are part of your lifestyle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lifestyle is more important than goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no external challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Without challenging yourself, life is boring and you&#39;ll probably degrade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&#39;s no external meaning of life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being a good man is important, and you can only try&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes you just live on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes all options are bad, with not choosing at all being the worst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downfalls shape you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We know almost nothing about life, so learning is important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I Tried to Write a Decent Desktop App</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-desktopapp.html" />
    <updated>2026-01-04T13:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-desktopapp.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;idea&quot;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting point for me was learning Go and writing a simple app, and I thought about operations on PDF files: merge, split, etc. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pdf24.org/en/&quot;&gt;pdf24&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most popular apps for Windows, so I reviewed its functions and UI/UX as a baseline. The idea was to program 3% of the most useful functions. Does pdf24 do the job? Sure. Would I use it on Windows if I needed to transform PDFs? Yes, it’s just not worth looking for viruses. Linux has &lt;a href=&quot;https://flathub.org/en/apps/search?q=pdf&quot;&gt;a number of desktop apps&lt;/a&gt; for PDF manipulation, by the way, but let’s just have another one. And I have some very specific ideas about UI/UX, but as I’m scratching my own itch here, it’s useful to write two sets of requirements: user requirements and dev requirements. You can check &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ikostas/pdf-tool&quot;&gt;the GitHub page&lt;/a&gt; for the result with screenshots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-requirements&quot;&gt;User requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most users may not care about the size of the app or some aspects of UI/UX if it gets the job done. Still, there are some nice things to have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hotkeys, because any app is faster with a keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast, because nobody likes waiting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern UI, which includes &#39;looking nice&#39;, but also being humble and similar to native UI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open multiple files at once for the merge operation; otherwise it’s unnerving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handle user input errors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intuitive in terms of simplicity, but also not allowing users to engage functions when it’s useless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UI doesn’t freeze while performing the task, which happens with some programs and the operating system can suggest closing the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple or (better) no installation procedure, which is especially relevant for Windows with limited permissions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The same program for Linux, Windows, and Mac – because users can get used to an app on one platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small download size is arguable now, but let it be&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dev-requirements&quot;&gt;Dev requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a (lazy and novice) developer, I’d like to have the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing less code (I mean, not like Java or GTK+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Threads for UI and tasks (Python and JS can only emulate them)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compile to Linux, Windows, and Mac without hassle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small app size matters for easy distribution as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convenient syntax for error handling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declarative UI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mature UI toolkit with all the functions a GUI app needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-choices&quot;&gt;Design choices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the language, Go ticks the boxes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Less code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Threads&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s natural to write error handling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross-compilation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the GUI toolkit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/cznic/tk9.0&quot;&gt;Tk9.0&lt;/a&gt; ticks the boxes as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declarative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Works on Linux, Windows, and Mac&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the functions for a GUI app included&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://pkg.go.dev/modernc.org/tk9.0@v1.73.0/themes/azure&quot;&gt;Azure theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hotkeys support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A file dialog to open multiple files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disabling buttons is easy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compact and fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the UI/UX itself, I decided to have a menu with buttons, and for each operation to have three sections in one window:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instructions with brief text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User input to open files and specify pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Messages about success or failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no pop-up messages, just one logically organized window, and Tk allows me to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;statistics&quot;&gt;Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m too lazy to measure how fast the app is; it actually uses the pdfcpu library, also written in Go. But it seems fast enough. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only statistics I have are file sizes and lines of code. The pdf24 distribution is 600 MB, being a lot more functional and with fancy stuff like PDF previews. My app is 29 MB for Windows and 46 MB for Linux, which includes debugging info. Without debugging info, the Linux app is 36 MB, which can be further reduced with upx to 20 MB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the lines of code, it’s 1004 lines, which is relatively small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the learning experience, I rewrote parts of the app multiple times and learned to prioritize clarity and trust the compiler. For Tk, it’s better to look at examples for guidelines, but what’s important for me is that it’s stable and doesn’t bring new bugs. One could complain about the absence of HTML: you need to emulate it with the included markup language and generate tags, but it was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Debian With Almost No Flatpak</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-debian.html" />
    <updated>2026-01-02T22:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2026-01-debian.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started with weird misclicks registered from my mouse, which turned out to be a hardware problem, but somehow led me to changing my distribution. At first I landed on CentOS, had problems setting up a printer (that was probably my skill issue), panicked and jumped to Debian. I&#39;ll write briefly about the reasons to choose Debian, but for the most part this hardware failure and migration was a reason to migrate all my stuff, data and programs, and to consider what I use and how. I hope it helps if you have similar use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;choosing-debian&quot;&gt;Choosing Debian&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from hardware issues, it seemed that the last Fedora update brought some dbus bugs. I can&#39;t prove it, for the last 2.5 years of using Fedora there were some bugs, but nothing too serious. Still, programs were crashing, memory leaks were standard and lots of programs could not keep up with the pace of Fedora development. Notably my favourite Gnome extensions couldn&#39;t keep up, and that was painful. Well, I need something with fast dnf (a package manager), but a little bit more stable, so it&#39;s CentOS Stream 10. I installed all the programs, some from RPM Fusion, others from Flathub. And in the end I started setting up my printer and failed. Maybe it can be set up, but I just want to point out a list of distributions for hp drivers (and CentOS had these drivers, but the older version, which didn&#39;t include my relatively new MFD):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/Q3p9N1GfRq-205.avif 205w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/Q3p9N1GfRq-205.webp 205w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/Q3p9N1GfRq-205.png&quot; alt=&quot;A distributions choice for HP drivers&quot; width=&quot;205&quot; height=&quot;633&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice is pretty wide, and there&#39;s no CentOS. Nowadays you can install just a binary, go for AppImage, Flatpak, but I still prefer a rpm or deb package as a first option. And CentOS dropped Gimp and LibreOffice in the favor of Flatpaks, if you&#39;re interested. And these are the most popular desktop apps, you can extrapolate to lots of other desktop apps to understand the situation. Maybe CentOS is a decent workstation desktop distribution, but not a home desktop distribution. You can still install nvidia drivers from RPM Fusion, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to choose then? As I remember OpenSuSe, zypper, the package manager, was very slow. Debian was fine, but I chose some strange iso and had to remove and install a lot of packages, and then my SSD died. And Debian doesn&#39;t like messing with external repos, they have a separate article about that. Well, let&#39;s try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I installed Debian, and this time I decided to start with the printer. I opened Gnome Settings, and the printer was just already there. That&#39;s what I call &#39;a desktop experience&#39;. To preserve my SSD I changed &lt;code&gt;vm.swappiness=10&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;/etc/sysctl.conf&lt;/code&gt; and turned on trim:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-bash&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; systemctl &lt;span class=&quot;token builtin class-name&quot;&gt;enable&lt;/span&gt; fstrim.timer
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; systemctl start fstrim.timer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not even sure that it&#39;s the right thing to do, I just pray for the best. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;display-and-gnome-setup&quot;&gt;Display and Gnome setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fonts are important, and the defaults in Debian are strange. But Debian Gnome desktop installation includes Gnome Tweaks, so I ended up with slight hinting and subpixel antialiasing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/uH4nzvXC-L-1102.avif 1102w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/uH4nzvXC-L-1102.webp 1102w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/uH4nzvXC-L-1102.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fonts setup&quot; width=&quot;1102&quot; height=&quot;762&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use exactly two Gnome extensions, I suppose they enhance the productivity greatly, and I have a meltdown when I can&#39;t use them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/ykeUcBEE2y-1091.avif 1091w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/ykeUcBEE2y-1091.webp 1091w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/ykeUcBEE2y-1091.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gnome extensions&quot; width=&quot;1091&quot; height=&quot;193&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined with autostart in Gnome Tweaks I have the desktop I need every time I log in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/AXF6f8P5w0-1042.avif 1042w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/AXF6f8P5w0-1042.webp 1042w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/AXF6f8P5w0-1042.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gnome autostarted apps&quot; width=&quot;1042&quot; height=&quot;553&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/l2wjrAE50b-757.avif 757w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/l2wjrAE50b-757.webp 757w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/l2wjrAE50b-757.png&quot; alt=&quot;Auto move setup&quot; width=&quot;757&quot; height=&quot;790&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;chrome&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing Chrome is the first thing I do, it works for the websites I need, it also works as a web version for Microsoft Teams and Zoom, and I really appreciate that. I also use a number of useful extensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/G6UM9VCn_F-1124.avif 1124w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/G6UM9VCn_F-1124.webp 1124w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/G6UM9VCn_F-1124.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome extensions&quot; width=&quot;1124&quot; height=&quot;804&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s exactly one scenario when I open Firefox, and it&#39;s regrettably common: when a website uses WordPress with an extension that breaks scrolling. Yes, people pay money for someone to make these websites. Animations are more important, you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s also a command to make Gnome open Chrome for &lt;code&gt;mailto:&lt;/code&gt; links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-bash&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;xdg-mime default google-chrome.desktop x-scheme-handler/mailto&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make it work, you need to click on a small sign in the addressbar when Gmail is opened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/kdDi55VNdM-322.avif 322w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/kdDi55VNdM-322.webp 322w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/kdDi55VNdM-322.png&quot; alt=&quot;Allow Gmail handle emails&quot; width=&quot;322&quot; height=&quot;274&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dev&quot;&gt;Dev&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing for me to do is to install a proper font for the terminal, and I&#39;ve got used to Source Code Pro. It has a strange name with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdfonts.com/&quot;&gt;Nerd symbols&lt;/a&gt;, which are used by neovim-Kickstart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/WPaUC9iytt-922.avif 922w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/WPaUC9iytt-922.webp 922w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://en.kovchinnikov.info/img/WPaUC9iytt-922.png&quot; alt=&quot;Source Code Pro with Nerd symbols&quot; width=&quot;922&quot; height=&quot;722&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the installation was straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neovim distribution is a bit too old for Kickstart, so I just installed a binary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&#39;t use Emacs much, but I have a good config and just in case I installed it from the standard repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also installed kitty as a terminal from a standard repo and added themes from github&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get the latest golang I installed a binary and updated paths in &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To get the latest node and npm I added a nodesource repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use gemini-cli, it&#39;s installed using npm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed tmux first, but then came across an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kovidgoyal/kitty/issues/391#issuecomment-638320745&quot;&gt;comment that with kitty you don&#39;t need tmux&lt;/a&gt;, so I removed tmux and learned kitty&#39;s hotkeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, I updated my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ikostas/misc&quot;&gt;config repo&lt;/a&gt; on github, if you are interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;communication&quot;&gt;Communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to evade Flatpak, I did the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telegram – installed it from a binary and made a symlink to &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discord and Zoom have debs, so I used them; I use them for gaming and learning German, accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;admin&quot;&gt;Admin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updating and helping some other people is important, so I use some specific apps for this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AnyDesk to access the screen, they have a deb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tailscale to ssh to a linux pc and do all the work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For myself I use borgmatic for backups, and again, it was just there, in the standard repos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I need VirtualBox, they have deb as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hobbies&quot;&gt;Hobbies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hobbies include recording a podcast and 3d-printing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&#39;t install Prusa Slicer yet, and it&#39;s the only program in the list that requires flatpak.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To record a podcast from the call or record a screencast I use OBS Studio, so I installed it from the repo, although they recommend a flatpak. The version is outdated (30 vs. 32 on Flathub), but we&#39;ll see.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To edit a podcast I use Reaper, it comes as a binary and just works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;games&quot;&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minecraft has a deb, but surprisingly it&#39;s outdated and doesn&#39;t work. So I downloaded &lt;code&gt;.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; and added a symlink to &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin&lt;/code&gt;. The strange thing is, you don&#39;t need a Java installed for Minecraft to work, because it installs Java.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For cloud gaming I use Boosteroid, they have a deb and it works, I&#39;ve played multiple hours. And they didn&#39;t pay me to mention them. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;misc&quot;&gt;Misc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some useful apps, which are in repos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Xournal++ to fill in PDF forms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VLC to have a media player with all the codecs (I think you need to enable &lt;code&gt;contrib&lt;/code&gt; repo in &lt;code&gt;/etc/apt/sources.list&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stow to have my configs in one place and update my github repo from there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the whole story of backing up and re-installing, I spent the most time with the following issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up a printer, which is relevant for CentOS only&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up Kickstart in neovim, as there were recent changes in neovim and it&#39;s not distro-specific (it&#39;s a temporary issue, as Kickstart is designed to be exactly one-command install)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything else went surprisingly smooth if you don&#39;t forget to move your ssh keys. :) I used Fedora as my playground for a lot of experiments, I used VirtualBox and Android Studio, and I must say Fedora is hard to break. Debian is not that hard to break when you start to add repos, but I didn&#39;t have to this time as the software versions are not that old, and it feels fast and stable. I hope I don&#39;t break it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moral of the story is that it&#39;s important for a distro to give all the developers to keep up with it. I hope I can work well even in Debian, as I still remember those painful moments of dealing with outdated software or apt complains about broken dependencies. Debian got a great tech stack from Fedora, I mean Gnome and systemd. So, now we can enjoy Debian. I suppose Debian also got some development boost from Google, which uses its Testing branch.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Happy Hacking New Year</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-12-hhny.html" />
    <updated>2025-12-22T18:43:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-12-hhny.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you, like me, have some free time during these Christmas holidays, I&#39;d suggest spending some time tinkering and learning. The feeling of accomplishing something while learning is, for me, the best feeling ever, so I have the following on the menu: learning the Go programming language, setting up remote support using Tailscale, a multi-seat setup on a single machine, and network boot. I&#39;ll describe the use cases and the reasoning behind these &amp;quot;projects&amp;quot;, so you can decide for yourself whether it&#39;s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short disclaimer: I describe all the efforts on Linux, and although you could make it work on other platforms as well, I won&#39;t be able to help you with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-go&quot;&gt;Learning Go&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invention of Go (which happened about 12 years ago, by the way) is, for me, a very important step in software development, because Go concepts try to fix the fundamental drawbacks of other languages. Here I&#39;ll describe the developer&#39;s perspective only – no performance discussion, although Go shines there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s start with the fundamental disadvantages of object-oriented programming (OOP), which were counter-intuitive for me at first: combining data and logic (methods) and inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we all know, a good programmer is a lazy programmer, but without clarity we get... well, Perl. Go is clear, splits data and logic, and doesn&#39;t use inheritance. And it prioritizes clarity. In my own experience, I had to write little code, it was functional and clear. So what&#39;s the problem with other languages?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python: OOP and no typing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaScript: cursed syntax and OOP and no typing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TypeScript: still cursed syntax and still OOP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java: too verbose and OOP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it turns out that a lack of typing is a problem as well. But let&#39;s turn to another thing: programming paradigms. There are functional, procedural, and object-oriented paradigms, and the truth is that Python and JS/TS are hybrid – you can use any paradigm you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started programming, I wrote Pascal and C code, and it was procedural. I read about the advantages of functional and object-oriented paradigms and I kind of still don&#39;t get it. You end up writing more unclear code. Go returned me to programming just logic, because logic is calling one procedure after another. And &lt;code&gt;switch/case&lt;/code&gt; is finally useful in Go, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Don&#39;t write a GUI app in Go&amp;quot;, I&#39;ve read in one book, and started using Tk 9.0. Tcl/Tk were introduced in 1989 – that&#39;s what I call &amp;quot;mature software&amp;quot;. And it has some markup language (ML), but you need to create and set up each tag; there are no function calls inside the tags. I decided to stay with Tk and generate my own tags, and that&#39;s where things got interesting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, just touching a technology introduced in 1989, you get to know how great engineering was at that time. It&#39;s very declarative, and the set of functions is enough for many apps. And look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pkg.go.dev/modernc.org/tk9.0@v1.73.0/themes/azure&quot;&gt;azure theme&lt;/a&gt; – it doesn&#39;t feel outdated at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, it felt cool to continue using this technology where others would switch to something like Wails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the UI is as abrupt as diarrhea, by the way, which I like. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that Go provides so much: it&#39;s completely free to play with, easy to start, powerful, and just feels &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; in lots of the aspects mentioned above. And this makes writing software fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tailscale&quot;&gt;Tailscale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve heard about Tailscale many times, but I ignored the ads as I didn&#39;t have a use case for it. The use case for me is remote support, but it can be a remote server of any kind. The goal was to have SSH access to the remote machine, and in case the machine is behind a router, you need to change the router setup. With Tailscale, you don&#39;t have to do that, as it creates a VPN and the machines think they are in the same local network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to connect to the remote machine, and in the worst-case scenario (an unqualified user), you could start with AnyDesk. It doesn&#39;t work with Wayland targets, by the way. So you create your user account with sudo privileges and install Tailscale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Tailscale needs to be up to connect to it, so some user-related setup is required – preferably a button. In the case of GNOME there&#39;s a GNOME extension. I had to deal with XFCE, so I ended up with a Bash script for Tailscale up/down and a button on the XFCE panel launching this script. And in case of SSH/RDP we need to make sure these services are running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, we can connect using SSH and first set up key-based authentication. Now it&#39;s a bit simpler to do admin tasks (update the system, for instance), but you could also add two enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; or another terminal multiplexer to run several tasks simultaneously and recover sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;mosh&lt;/code&gt; if you connect from an unstable network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multi-seat-setup&quot;&gt;Multi-seat setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A multi-seat setup in the base variant means 2 monitors, 2 keyboards, and 2 mice connected to one PC. As a rule, you start with a video card with 2 outputs. You can add more, but there are some limiting factors: the number of video cards you can install, whether you hit CPU/RAM/HDD limits, and the length of cables for keyboards/mice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3-seat setups were used at schools; they obviously don&#39;t fit heavy gaming scenarios. This configuration is a budget-friendly way to get computing power for 2 home-office workers, for example. Wayland does not support this configuration. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.debian.org/Multi_Seat_Debian_HOWTO&quot;&gt;Debian how-to&lt;/a&gt; is a great place to start. Assuming the average CPU load is 0%, it&#39;s a natural lifehack for two people sitting next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;network-boot&quot;&gt;Network boot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network boot means having a server with OS images and booting other machines from it. It allows you to have a diskless machine with an NFS server, which is relevant for old hardware, and it also simplifies user data backups. But you will need to set up a DHCP server to point to a server with images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can combine diskless workstations with remote access like RDP to use the server&#39;s CPUs. The docs for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tldp.org/HOWTO/Network-boot-HOWTO/index.html&quot;&gt;TLDP project&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.fedoraproject.org/en-US/fedora/f36/install-guide/advanced/Network_based_Installations/&quot;&gt;Fedora&lt;/a&gt; are probably helpful in this regard. And yes, setting up a network server for installations is also a nice option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s assumed that hard drives are cheap and network boot has fewer use cases now, but for me the whole diskless option was eye-opening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you learned something new reading this article. I don&#39;t provide detailed instructions in order not to copy or misinterpret instructions from other sites (which are also updated). When &amp;quot;learning&amp;quot; hits &amp;quot;useful&amp;quot;, it can bring happiness – so happy hacking New Year to you!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>There Will Be Signs</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-12-signs.html" />
    <updated>2025-12-04T11:58:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-12-signs.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d like to dive into the &amp;quot;toxic behaviour&amp;quot; topic, notably &amp;quot;psychopathic&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;careerist&amp;quot; (narcissistic) colleague types, based on my experience. The reason I feel a need to write about it is that from my viewpoint such behaviour doesn&#39;t get enough attention and thus doesn&#39;t meet counter-measures, we just let it slip. It&#39;s their responsibility to demonstrate this behaviour, but it&#39;s our responsibility to respond accordingly. And I need to start with a couple of disclaimers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&#39;s a great book &amp;quot;5 Types of People Who Can Ruin Your Life&amp;quot; by Bill Eddy. If you have a choice to continue reading this article or to start reading the book, I&#39;d prefer the book. It was my fault not to read this book earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#39;m not a psychologist in any way; I can misuse psychological terms out of my ignorance, so you should not trust me on this matter. The facts I write about, though, happened in real life and people got hurt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I write about this misbehaviour, it doesn&#39;t mean I don&#39;t have it. I&#39;m not the one to accuse, but I could warn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What causes these types of behaviour is outside of the scope of this article, and I&#39;d recommend guarding your own boundaries rather than digging into that, although it&#39;s a childhood trauma as a rule of thumb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The issue is serious, and from my practice two things worked: giving firm feedback to a person to stop this behaviour or excluding this person from the team. Both recipes work if you have power; if you don&#39;t, you have to decide for yourself to tolerate or to run – I felt regret for those who decided to stay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t say that these types don&#39;t bring value; they in fact can bring more value than others. It just doesn&#39;t justify, for me, destroying other people&#39;s lives. If you are in a superior position and you think about hiring such a person and giving him/her a team to manage, it means leaving your team with the abuser and giving this abuser the power, including the power to hide his/her actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s move on: each paragraph in the following text presents evidence. As a rule of thumb (and as a Chinese saying goes), one can be nothing, two should make you think, three is a system. When you have three, it takes some courage to admit whom you are dealing with and to plan your actions accordingly. So, don&#39;t panic (C).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-psycho&quot;&gt;A psycho&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleagues suffer and complain to each other about this person. A behaviour is not a one-off thing; it&#39;s repeated, so several persons usually experience this. But this is really dumb, because others can see a pattern. By the way, please note that I mentioned &amp;quot;complained to each other&amp;quot;, so they are afraid of this person and afraid to escalate the issue to actually resolve it. Returning to patterns, something else is more dangerous and more powerful: he/she chooses one victim and demonstrates dysfunctional behaviour with this person only, while all the others can believe in his/her good intent and know nothing of his/her humiliating actions. But there&#39;s a pattern: after the victim leaves, he/she chooses another victim, so you can notice the pattern over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power is a drug to such a person, and he/she understands power as an ability to micro-manage and to manipulate people. These are completely different issues, and it&#39;s above my paygrade to elaborate on manipulation, but micro-management is simple: insisting on how you should do something, demanding immediate reactions, so you should leave everything and run (literally), repeating requests within a minute if action is not taken, using different channels to demand actions like calling and messages and knocking on the window – you can easily get a nervous tic from these actions alone. Micro-management is also confused with understanding the matter and asking profound questions, and that&#39;s actual competence. You feel safe communicating in these scenarios if you are competent and have nothing to hide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impression over being a good person, hypocrisy. Culturally, many of us are taught a lot more about producing an impression than about being a good person (there&#39;s also a significant difference between being nice and being kind), so many of us do that. It doesn&#39;t make us psychos (maybe a little bit, and you definitely do yourself a favor if you stop behaving like this). For me, the evidence is a difference between how good and how bad the person can be depending on how much power he/she has in a particular situation. And the rule for me is this: if this difference makes you vomit, it&#39;s bad. Another point is that a person can treat his/her team badly and proceed like nothing happened. That&#39;s another issue; psychos lack empathy, so they don&#39;t feel the damage done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-careerist-narcissistic&quot;&gt;A careerist / narcissistic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every task, he/she first thinks about how it&#39;s going to advance his/her career and loses interest if it doesn&#39;t. These people are obsessed with career, and it&#39;s even funny to observe that they start career-related discussions for every small task. It decreases efficiency as they require detailed explanation in relation to their career, and these discussions obviously cost time and money. But they lose vigilance, so it&#39;s easy to notice. Regretfully, too much attention to career can be normalized in some organizations, so it becomes difficult to define what is &amp;quot;too much&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They try to lick bosses’ asses, and they are kind of systematic about this: they remember small personal details about bosses and their family members, try to be useful, always emphasize subordination, and leverage all the human weaknesses they can. These techniques are described and even recommended to build a career, but it&#39;s not healthy. They distribute more effort to licking somebody&#39;s ass than to doing the job. It&#39;s a pity this behaviour is normalized, tolerated, and recommended. Again, the extent is the question here, so I use the &amp;quot;vomit rule&amp;quot; here as well. It&#39;s easy to notice when actual performance falls because of focus on non-work-related issues, but these people are clever and usually performance doesn&#39;t fall. It&#39;s easy to notice how careerists spend lots of time with their bosses, a lot more than is required for the job to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They overwork a lot and overemphasize their hard work. First, speaking about yourself too much is a definition of narcissism. Second, working in a team and speaking about yourself is nonsense. Third, taking too much work and not planning it adequately is a planning disability and should not be encouraged, but greedy persons do encourage that. And fourth, a healthy KPI system in a healthy organization catches the results, not speaking about the process, so it&#39;s a bad system if it works the other way. A careerist doesn&#39;t use magic; he/she exploits the system when the system allows him/her to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics is a big thing for these persons. I mean, it is sure a thing, but there&#39;s a job to be done as well (I assume). It&#39;s again about prioritising politics over everything else, getting involved in politics above his/her paygrade, a willingness to sacrifice everything human-related for the sake of some political advancement. Sure, that&#39;s the world we live in, but it&#39;s also the amount of politics we allow ourselves to have. I&#39;ve seen large organizations where people were able to do big changes without politics or small organizations where politics prevail – guess which organization is more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So politics is a lot about influence, and they see someone doing anything even related to their sphere as losing influence, it&#39;s a tragedy, so they don&#39;t let anyone in and defend &amp;quot;their&amp;quot; field furiously. The problem is that it&#39;s not a private field; it&#39;s about the organization. This battle for influence can be misunderstood as zeal in work. I see it like this: if a person is competent, he/she is normally friendly and willing to tell anyone about the work he/she is doing. When you see hostility and concealment of information, for me it&#39;s a hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These persons also are willing to extend their influence, and their own lack of competence plays no role here. If you allow it, you get incompetent people doing the job, and you may even not notice it until something critical fails. I won&#39;t elaborate here on careerists&#39; skills to blame others; the point is that for some reason the organization as a system and the managers allow incompetent persons to take the job. The moment you stop matching competence and the area of responsibility, you are in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience, top management can be filled with psychos, and if this issue is not addressed directly, it spreads, because almost no KPIs show the problem, sometimes even employee turnover rate, as employees can be held in place using fear. And I also can&#39;t suggest a direct cure other than knowing people and taking an insight into what&#39;s going on in teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Careerists are less problematic as they are easier to spot. But giving them what they want, justifying their behaviour makes them advance and enlarge their influence. People are not idiots; they totally get who is promoted and why, so moving careerists up erodes a company&#39;s values when they exist. The funniest thing I saw was when a company full of careerists and greedy people collapsed and they blamed each other. It happens, and you don&#39;t even need an economic crisis for this. It&#39;s just the self-destruction they carry in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We Can Make the Internet a Better Place</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-11-internet.html" />
    <updated>2025-11-13T13:50:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-11-internet.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days of the Internet, it was made and populated by users with extremely high intellect, and they cared to share something valuable. Then commercialization started, and here we are: one-page reviews generated by LLMs and filled with ads, acid-colored landing pages, business-card-type websites thinking they are apps and failing to do... scrolling, and so on. I&#39;d like to express some ideas obvious to me, as the current state of the Internet is quite mature in its &amp;quot;commercialization&amp;quot; phase, which brings us ugly and unusable websites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility and functionality are underrated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the other hand, animation and all the &amp;quot;dynamic&amp;quot; parts of websites are overrated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monetization is a tricky thing; addressing it directly can hurt all the parties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s get to it – I&#39;ve been collecting evidence for so long...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By accessibility we often mean that the content on the page is semantically marked and thus people with disabilities can use screen readers and other tools to access it. It&#39;s a great thing, but in my opinion there&#39;s a lot more to the simplicity of HTML: it can be searched, it loads fast, it can be cached by the browser. If you have a fairly responsive server that renders HTML, or a static HTML page, it will feel faster and just better to use than a website with some heavy front-end. It&#39;s just so simple that nothing can beat it. Creating React.js and other front-end UIs is often justified by a better UX, but a fast-loading page &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; the best experience. Besides, the more code – the more errors. Sometimes the bigger app doesn&#39;t load correctly, and UX suffers again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;functionality&quot;&gt;Functionality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#39;t justify one thing in the modern Internet: why do websites offering mostly text and graphics deem themselves &amp;quot;apps&amp;quot;? It has something to do with the abundance of resources, because they are not apps: newspapers, business-card-type company websites, blogs. If we ask ourselves &amp;quot;what do we need to deliver this content as accessibly as possible,&amp;quot; put the point and draw a straight line – that could actually be a great website. But in reality this does not happen, and we get bloatware and functions we don&#39;t need. &amp;quot;But we have these reactive apps, we should use them&amp;quot; – no. If you have a modern cool technology, its use still should be justified. We have a &amp;quot;default&amp;quot; situation: a WordPress site is default – I&#39;ve seen a dozen with broken scrolling in Chrome. Why? Well, it&#39;s WordPress, everybody uses it, it should be working. Should we have tested it? Oh, no...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-entry-barrier&quot;&gt;An entry barrier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days of the Internet, if you needed to put something out there, learning HTML was mandatory. If you wanted to put something on a forum, you&#39;d probably write in HTML or some other markup language as well. By the way, you needed a computer to do that – smartphones were not there – so you had to figure out a way to get through all the specs of a computer, allocate money, buy it, bring it home, and connect it to the Internet, which could be a challenge as well. The absence of the entry barrier obviously erodes the quality of content, whether it&#39;s irrelevant conclusions about economics, medicine, racial discrimination, or computers and the Internet itself. And we have bots, which are able to amplify the most inappropriate conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving bots aside, as it&#39;s mostly a technical issue to identify and disable them, are these &amp;quot;website builders&amp;quot; necessarily a good thing? I look at some &amp;quot;over-monetized&amp;quot; blogs, and I don&#39;t think so. They will eventually disappear, but the broken search will not be fixed, though. The damage was done, and I&#39;m not going to even try to prevent future damage. Let&#39;s address a particular issue: a company is going to pay for a website &amp;quot;without diving into details.&amp;quot; Don&#39;t do it – it&#39;s not that hard to find someone who knows HTML and also knows why WordPress is a dead end. IT is not outstanding; it&#39;s the same as any other area: applying competence to the task. If you apply no competence, you get a bad result, even if you have money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;over-monetization&quot;&gt;Over-monetization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I deeply believe that direct monetization with ads or a paywall is an easy, widespread, and wrong solution to the problem. Direct monetization hurts – it destroys the trust between the author and the reader. And this trust has value by itself: you could get recommended and land your next job or a big project because of it. Why would you exchange this trust for some insignificant money flow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing is content marketing, and it&#39;s widely used: you have a company blog with high-quality content, and your company gets more attention because of this blog. It doesn’t make any sense to have ads in this blog. But a personal blog or any other blog could work the same way: people are not idiots – they can connect the dots between a paid service and the blog content, and they will follow the paid service if they need it. In general, I think treating people like idiots is at the core of &amp;quot;over-monetization,&amp;quot; and it&#39;s just a bad strategy. Sure, it can work short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;collective-blogs&quot;&gt;Collective blogs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collective blogs are great, and I honestly think we need more of them. Not just social networks like Reddit, but more profound articles like dev.to. It takes some effort to implement: you need an engine with ratings and karma, as well as moderators to look after the content, plus a policy on what&#39;s allowed and what&#39;s not. But it makes me so happy to visit these kinds of resources. I&#39;d say that since 2003 I&#39;ve spent most of my Internet time on these blogs, contributing my own articles – and this &amp;quot;community feeling&amp;quot; is amazing. Again, it&#39;s not that much about monetization, and not that direct. People can draw the line between an author representing a company and the company itself, so it works quite well in terms of content marketing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;privacy-and-cookies&quot;&gt;Privacy and cookies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law about cookies was just bad; I wonder when the EU will finally admit it. Privacy online is possible when you boot Tails (a Linux distribution) or something like that, and Snowden&#39;s case proves it, as he used it and they didn&#39;t catch him. :) All proprietary operating systems, including Android, are a grave to privacy – people should just get it at some point. That&#39;s all I have to say about it, and now I use the &amp;quot;I don&#39;t care about cookies&amp;quot; plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;css&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSS is a simple language, yet creating good CSS is hard. It should do at least the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look nice and appealing to people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be accessible in terms of free space between elements, font size, and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a mobile-friendly version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a nice-looking website shows respect for the people visiting it, and design is hard. It&#39;s a separate discipline, and people need time to learn it. Yet there are plenty of great free CSS libraries. They cover all the points above and even more, and they assume customization, so your website won’t look like all the others. It’s great to be kind to people – let your website be kind to your visitors, just use tested CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My nostalgia is not based on how the web used to look or even how simple it was. It&#39;s about people following their curiosity and a strong wish to make the web a better place with technology, spread knowledge, and lead other people with ideas from the frontier of scientific discovery. People know that money follows value, but they still panic and try to pursue money directly, putting 80% or more effort into marketing. You can say no to this when you choose what content to consume, what websites to bookmark, or what to contribute – your content or your effort – to build a better Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Learning Programming in 2026</title>
    <link href="https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-11-programming.html" />
    <updated>2025-11-03T08:55:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://en.kovchinnikov.info/2025-11-programming.html</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are at the end of 2025, so it&#39;s time to make some plans for 2026. And these plans for many people depend on the question: is learning programming still a thing? I&#39;m not working as a developer and I&#39;m not discussing the trend where lots of juniors have been dismissed and few are hired, with senior developers still in demand, though. I&#39;m talking about the value of thinking and problem-solving, as well as the ability to understand what&#39;s going on with computer systems and make the right decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost like how security rules are written with blood, history is not about having a visionary and going in the right direction (although that was true with Unix and C++). It&#39;s often about testing all the variants and learning &amp;quot;the hard way&amp;quot; how they fail, so I&#39;ll bring some real-life &amp;quot;Halloween&amp;quot; stories to your attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-wrong-decisions&quot;&gt;The wrong decisions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first story happened to me in my first job. We had a team of three people: a project manager, a developer, and me as a consultant. We were implementing Microsoft Dynamics AX ERP system (now called Microsoft 365 Finance and Operations), so it was around 2006. The situation was not standard: we needed to inject money into logistics transactions and the financial contour of the system. It turned out that our project manager had a plan which was completely unfeasible, but he didn&#39;t share it with his team. The takeaway is not about teamwork though – it&#39;s about planning something when at least someone knows how it works under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s no surprise this happens again: making decisions when no one actually knows what&#39;s going on. I&#39;ve been in hundreds if not thousands of meetings, and the most frustrating ones are when no one understands what&#39;s going on and, in their ignorance, doesn&#39;t want to invite a subject matter expert to clarify the issue – because, well, it would reveal their incompetence. That can lead to anything from an incident to a disaster, and that&#39;s what the next two cases are about. The new idea, common for both cases, is the formula &amp;quot;incompetent person + language model = competent person,&amp;quot; which doesn’t work out at all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Tea app, a social network for women, faced a massive personal data leak after boasting about extensive use of language-model-generated code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The AWS hub outage, noticed by almost everyone using the Internet: again, AWS had heavily promoted using language-model-generated code before that. A software bug was cited as the reason for the outage – I don&#39;t believe that in 2025 qualified programmers and testers are unable to push reliable code to production, but language models certainly are not able to do that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend toward language-model-generated code is like a locomotive – impossible to stop right now – so we&#39;ll see more outages for sure. Another funny thing is that some developers advertise themselves as &amp;quot;re-writing&amp;quot; AI-generated code, which is exhausting, by the way. You face at least 2–4x more code than there should be – code implementing features no one asked for, and not implementing security or reliability features... well, because no one asked for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-programming&quot;&gt;What is programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d like to redefine programming, and my definition is not in line with a basic Computer Science (CS) course, regretfully:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s about learning a programming language, but you need to learn at least one more language other than Python. Python is concise and simple, but it&#39;s so similar to human language, and the interpreter is so friendly in reporting errors, that it feels almost like cheating. With not enough &lt;strong&gt;resistance&lt;/strong&gt;, you don’t get enough &lt;strong&gt;exercise&lt;/strong&gt;, which is what working with computers is about – developing a certain level of problem-solving ability. So, I suggest learning something harder like C++, Java, or JavaScript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s about learning markup languages as well: HTML, Markdown, LaTeX. The ability to see structure when you read markup code is important, and these languages are the basis of modern IT. After learning front-end, I also changed my perspective on user interfaces: the back-end defines what capabilities you have, but representation matters, and you should at least have an opinion on front-end technologies like Angular, Vue, or React.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s about learning SQL, which is included in CS courses, as &lt;strong&gt;logic&lt;/strong&gt; is often not about transforming data but about storing and extracting it – and that may not be obvious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s about learning the basics of how the Internet and networks in general work. What are the protocol layers? Why would you prefer the Internet over a local network? When computers start to interact with each other, security questions arise: what level of security are we able to achieve and promise to our customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s about learning the basics of operating systems – how they function, what layers they have, and why Linux is better (just joking). Working in IT implies having some outlook, knowing some history: what about microkernel architecture, for example? And history, especially computer history, has a lot of lessons to learn from – why something &amp;quot;ugly&amp;quot; works in the long term, and some architecturally beautiful or overhyped concepts fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even that’s not enough: there are programming patterns, architectures, and specific security vulnerabilities, which make the features visible to the user only about 10% of the iceberg. So yes, programming is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-ai&quot;&gt;What about AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry for repeating myself, but I&#39;ll write it again just in case you don’t know: we don’t have AI yet. Just listen to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/episode/3zAXRCFrHPShU4MuuIx4V5?si=LO8baLI5RxeLmrm0f5vNUg&quot;&gt;podcast with Richard Sutton&lt;/a&gt;: language models use knowledge – they are unable to learn, even like animals do. Yes, they can pass Turing’s test, but it’s still emulation of intellect rather than having it. True intellect is called AGI (artificial general intelligence). Forecasts vary – one of the latest episodes of the same &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/episode/3iIYVmmhXwh3fOumypWVpC?si=B-Sk4SSVQbmi7k7hMDneNA&quot;&gt;podcast with Andrej Karpathy&lt;/a&gt; is called &amp;quot;AGI is still a decade away.&amp;quot; I’m not sure if I’m going to listen to it – it sounds pessimistic. Or optimistic – depending on how you look at the path behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-professions-will-disappear&quot;&gt;What professions will disappear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d recommend listening to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/episode/6vBr2kDnmrUu17xdiRVbXR?si=KSjKbq_zQ_W6JTG8OTVotQ&quot;&gt;podcast with Elon Musk&lt;/a&gt;, although it’s boring at times. Elon states that all professions working with computers will disappear. I’d say that working with requirements is the most difficult part, even for humans. In the real world, product managers and project managers do this job. Being one of them, I can see the demand falling. Can developers do this job? Yes, sure. The great devs I know were great at working with requirements (and architecture). The work model just tends to be more primitive now: creating a prototype at each step and moving forward based on feedback. It’s not that bad – if &amp;quot;the managers&amp;quot; are so expensive, this model can even be more cost-effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-side-history-quest&quot;&gt;A side history quest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of IT is rather short, but I&#39;d like to ask a question: when did humanity make progress in general? I believe it happened when highly talented and motivated people (self-)assembled in teams and faced challenging tasks. For me, the case &amp;quot;Windows vs. Linux&amp;quot; is clear and closed – and that’s what happened (in my humble opinion). In the early days of Linux, FreeBSD was also a thing, but for me, the turning point from FreeBSD to Linux was the journaling system ReiserFS, which boosted filesystem performance on Linux. Windows filesystem performance looked just ridiculous, and from a performance viewpoint, Windows made no sense because of its outdated multitasking model. So in this case, engineers (or developers) won over &amp;quot;managers,&amp;quot; whether they were managing products, projects, finances, or marketing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s happening now is like &amp;quot;the managers&amp;quot; striking back using language models to get rid of devs. Look at Windows now: it’s clearly a follower, copying Linux tech – be it WSL (Windows Subsystem for Linux) or PowerShell with its CLI approach (which existed before Linux, I must say). To cover Windows’ grave with asphalt, they even introduced ads in Windows – so even more Windows supporters are pissed off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not &amp;quot;devs vs. managers&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;devs vs. language models.&amp;quot; It’s &amp;quot;true vs. fake.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-s-intelligence&quot;&gt;What’s intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think intelligence reveals itself in solving problems, and there’s no other way to train intelligence than by solving problems – always raising the bar. Programming is great for training intelligence because, in real life, you can cut corners: people can abandon their own requirements if you’re convincing enough, you can motivate people to work overtime to compensate for bad planning, and so on. IT is ideal in terms of &amp;quot;strict requirements&amp;quot;: you’re unable to cut corners there – it works or it doesn’t. It also teaches a very important concept of &amp;quot;good enough,&amp;quot; which I think is underappreciated in real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you are suffering while learning, you’re probably on the right path, because it means you have a challenging task. By the way, choosing a &amp;quot;good enough&amp;quot; solution can also be quite painful for us perfectionists. :) That’s the reason why people choose to write programs using a language literally called &amp;quot;Brainf*ck,&amp;quot; or use Raspberry Pi – a computer with very limited resources. Because you raise the bar – not by making the task more complex, but by limiting the resources or the toolset. And it seems that it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-the-challenges-for-programming&quot;&gt;What are the challenges for programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, what if you’re trying to create an app and you’re not taking the fast, easy, and wrong path of generating code with a language model? Let’s start with the requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to deliver fast because you still compete with language models :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to deliver cheap for the same reason – and I’m not talking about outsourcing here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your code needs to be stable and secure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think choosing the right framework is the right place to start. It shouldn’t be too fresh and undocumented, but it should leverage recent advancements to... well, write less code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example and talk about a web app. Django, Ruby on Rails, and Laravel gained popularity for a reason – because (and DHH was right here) they solve an &amp;quot;end-to-end&amp;quot; problem. In the JS world, it’s a little more chaotic and &amp;quot;DIY&amp;quot;-like; I’ve actually lost track of what’s going on. :) It’s bad to start learning programming with a framework, but it’s so nice when you already have one you need. And I’m really inspired by how wide the choice is now, especially compared to the situation just a few years ago. Anyway, code generators within frameworks – when you know what you’re doing – are far better than copying code from a chatbot. Please, for the sake of humanity, don’t do that. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something else inspires me even more than the progress with the hardware and software we have compared to 1999, when I started playing with FreeBSD (and everybody was terrified of the “year 2000 problem,” ha-ha). It’s how much you have to play with now, and how many resources you have to satisfy your curiosity. Codecademy doesn’t pay me, but it’s hard not to mention their free resources to learn coding in any language, including Rust, Kotlin, and Bash. And this experience – to feel what’s on the edge of software development right now – is quite satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>